ORIGINAL STORY BY NATSU HYUUGA
（原作：日向夏）
About today's plans,
然后 关于今天的计划
we'll have the Mid Festival in the afternoon.
午后将会举行中祀
Sure.
好
I have a general idea of what you're thinking about,
您在想什么 我大概想象得到
but don't forget about work.
但也请别忘了工作
I know.
我明白
Sir Lihaku. What's wrong?
李白大人 怎么了吗？
Something bad has happened.
发生了一件麻烦的事
Something bad?
麻烦的事？
Remember the fire in the warehouse?
之前仓库不是有场小火灾吗？
-Yes. -On the same day, also this.
-对 -在同一天
There was a theft at a different warehouse.
另一间仓库似乎遭窃了
They must've taken advantage of all the commotion that night.
犯人一定是趁着骚动下手的
A looter at a fire, huh?
趁火打劫吗？
What was stolen?
被偷了什么？
I guess this is a behind-closed-doors discussion.
看来是得避人耳目的话题呢
We lost some ritual items.
祭器不见了
Multiples of them, in fact.
而且好像被偷了好几件
Were they stored that carelessly?
管理这么松散吗？
I'm not entirely sure myself, but…
我也不是很清楚
We don't have any knowledgeable managers at the moment.
现在正巧没有深谙这些东西的管理人
We had one that passed away last year.
他似乎在去年过世了
What about the current manager?
那现在的管理人呢？
I'm sure he has general knowledge.
他应该知道些大概吧？
Apparently, he got food poisoning a while back.
他在不久前食物中毒了
Food poisoning?
食物中毒？
He got it from his favorite type of seaweed.
起因是他爱吃的海藻
He's unconscious, and can't go back to work.
结果到现在都没清醒 无法回到岗位
So we're in a bind.
很伤脑筋啊
This sounds familiar.
听起来好耳熟
Could that be the bureaucrat who loves delicacies?
您说的该不会是 一位爱吃珍馐的官员吧？
How do you know?
你为什么知道？
It's a long story.
因为各种原因
A theft that occurred at the same time as a fire.
在火灾同时发生窃案
The manager of the warehouse, who was absent due to food poisoning.
仓库的管理人 也因为食物中毒不在岗位
It's too strange to be a coincidence.
说是偶然也太不可思议了
What kind of person was the manager who passed away last year?
那位去年过世的管理人 是怎么样的人呢？
I know he was famous for being straight-laced.
我只知道他是位耿直出名的大叔
I can't think of the name.
但不记得名字了
I know that he loved sweets.
只记得他喜爱甜食之类的
Could it be Sir Kounen?
该不会是浩然大人吧？
Right, that's it!
对 就是他
Hey, how do you know these things?
喂 你怎么都知道啊？
It's a long story.
因为各种原因
This must be the sweet-toothed high official
以前从壬氏大人那儿听来
that I heard about from Sir Jinshi,
喜爱甜食的耿直高官
who died from overconsumption of salt.
因为摄取过多盐分而过世的男子
Could this all be just coincidence?
这全都是偶然吗？
Each incident looks like an accident,
乍看之下 每件事都是意外
but what if they were all orchestrated
但若是有人为了某个目的
by someone with some kind of purpose?
而故意引发这些事件的话…
So, did you need me for something?
话说回来 您找我是什么事呢？
Oh, right!
对 进入正题
This thing that you gave me…
这是你给我保管的东西
Oh, from the fire.
哦 火灾那时的
I tried to return it,
我本来要物归原主
but the owner returned it to me, saying he didn't want it.
但物品主人却退还给我 说他不要了
I thought it was precious, since it's a high-quality item.
这是高级品 我以为是很重要的东西呢
Apparently, he got it from some court lady.
好像是某个女官送给他的
A court lady?
女官？
Isn't it strange?
不觉得奇怪吗？
Why would someone give a warehouse guard something like this?
为什么要特地 送仓库看守人这种东西？
Apparently,
为什么仓库看守人
this guard escorted a court lady
会将在夜里独自行走的女官
outside the palace since she was walking alone in the dark.
护送到城外呢？
This smoking pipe was given to him then to thank him.
这根烟管就是当时的谢礼
If you received something this nice,
若是收到这么贵重的东西
you'd want to use it right away.
或许会想立刻用看看呢
Start a fire, and sneak into a different warehouse
引发火灾 在戒备变得薄弱时
when the security is sparse.
潜进另一间仓库
If the court lady
若一开始目标就是如此
gifted the guard with the smoking pipe to accomplish this…
女官才将烟管送给仓库看守人的话…
Sir Lihaku, who was this court lady?
李白大人 那位女官是谁？
I asked for details,
我详细地打听了一番
but she was wearing a scarf, so her face was hidden.
但她似乎围着围巾 将脸遮住了
Perhaps she was hiding her face on purpose.
说不定是为了提前隐藏自己的长相呢
Could be.
有可能
Apparently, she was tall for a woman,
不过 听说以女子来说很高挑
and smelled of medicine.
身上好像还有股药味
You're not tall, so I know it wasn't you.
虽然从身高判断 我知道不是你
But do you have any ideas?
但你有什么线索吗？
The scent of medicine,
药的味道
a tall court lady…
高挑的女官
Don't speak on speculation alone.
不能凭着臆测推论哦
Other than the incidents and accidents you listed,
除了刚才提到的事故和事件
did anything else strange happen?
还有发生什么神秘难解的事情吗？
That's easy for you to say, but…
就算你这么问…
Would looking into that dig anything up?
我去调查的话 会有什么发现吗？
Maybe.
也许会
-Maybe not. -Which is it?
-也许不会 -到底会不会啊？
Two coincidences could happen at once.
两种偶然同时发生很常见
Maybe even three.
同时发生三件偶然也不是不可能
But if these coincidences keep adding up,
但如果好几件偶然重叠起来
making it not so coincidental,
就会有成为必然的时候
and if the tall court lady was at the center of all this,
如果在必然中 有一位像高挑女官的人物
what would that mean?
会怎么样呢？
Even if the court lady named Suirei becomes the central figure,
这样一来 即使浮现出翠苓那样的女官
it has nothing to do with me.
也不关我的事了
I see! You're smarter than you look!
原来如此 看不出来你这么聪明！
You're as strong as you look, Sir Lihaku.
李白大人倒是和看起来一样强壮呢
Please go easy on me.
请您注意一下力道
You look like you're having fun.
你们好像很开心啊
We're not having fun.
并没有很开心啊
I'll be on my way then.
我先告辞了！
You seem very close to that military officer.
你跟那个武官关系很好呢
Do I?
有吗？
Some things were bothering him
他只是有些在意的事
so he wanted to ask me some questions about it.
所以来问我而已
These incidents
这次的事情
could possibly be related to Sir Jinshi.
也不能说和壬氏大人没有关系
Could I bother you with the details?
能否听小的详细说来？
Those are some strange connections, indeed.
奇妙地连结在一起了呢
Yes.
对
So, what do you think it means?
那么 你觉得有什么秘密？
I don't know.
不晓得
It seems as if they're trying to set several traps,
与其确保事件一次成功
hoping one might work, rather than planning for
犯人宁可设下许多陷阱 有几个成功就行了
one big incident.
看起来更像是这样
I see. So they might have set up other traps.
那样的话 也还可能有其他陷阱了
Though it's hard to say for certain.
小的无法断言
With all of the incidents, it's hard to say whether they were planned or not.
这些案件都难以判断是罪案或是意外
It's still entirely possible that they were all coincidences.
也无法否定只是重重偶然的可能性
You're not interested?
你没兴趣吗？
Interested?
兴趣？
I'm a mere maidservant.
我只是个婢女
I only do as I'm told.
只会按照吩咐做事罢了
Then, what about this?
那么这样如何？
The other day, when I visited some trading merchants,
前几天我去贸易商那边巡视时
I heard of an interesting item going around.
听说进了些有趣的东西
This is what it's called.
名字叫做这个
Calculus bovis are cow gallstones, a type of medicine!
牛黄是一种药材 是牛的胆结石
It's a top quality product that can only be obtained from one in 1,000 cows!
据说一千头牛中只有一头能取得 是最高级的药材！
Could it be, he would give it to me?
难道要赐给我吗？
Is it true? He's not bluffing?
真的吗？不是骗人的吧？
-Do you want it? -Please!
-想要吗？ -想要！
Xiaomao.
小猫
Excuse me, sir.
我失礼了
Looks like you're all in.
看来是有干劲了呢
You'll really give this to me?
真的能赐给我吗？
Depends on how well you do.
得看你办得如何了 逐一处理这些消息吧
I understand.
明白了
As you wish, Sir Jinshi!
就照壬氏大人的意思办
All right then, Gaoshun. Get right to it!
那么高顺 拜托你准备了
This is the incident from the other day.
这是前几天的事件
The official who got food poisoning was from the Board of Rites.
食物中毒的官员是礼部人员
If I remember correctly, the Board of Rites
说到礼部 没记错的话
manages education and foreign affairs.
应该是掌管教育和外交的官署
Only if I actually studied to become a court lady.
女官考试要是有认真准备就好了
I'll leave these here.
我放在这儿哦
Thank you.
谢谢
Not a problem. Ask me anything
不会 要是有哪儿不明白
you don't know.
随时可以问我
What kind of position is this?
这个官职是什么呢？
This position works with festivities.
这是掌管祭祀的官职
Festivities, huh?
祭祀？
Do you have anything to write with?
您有纸笔之类的吗？
Oh, yes.
有
Festivities, festivities…
祭祀…
The food-poisoned official and Sir Kounen
食物中毒的官员 浩然大人
both worked with festivities.
都是与祭祀相关的官吏
And if the smoke pipe incident
若是烟管的那件骚动
was a way to ensure that the ritual items were stolen…
是为了确保能偷出祭器的话
There must be a place where these "coincidental" events meet
那么这些 被伪装成偶然的事件重迭起来
to create an "inevitable."
一定会有发生“必然”之处
If the ritual items were stolen with this much planning,
会用到费了如此功夫偷走的祭器
it means they're used for big festivities.
是有相当规模的祭祀
Larger than Mid Festival.
应该是中祀以上
I should look into when that will take place.
应该把何时举行都查个明白才是
Now that I think of it, Sir Jinshi did purification ceremonies often.
对了 壬氏大人也很常进行祓濯
If you're interested in festivities,
要是对祭祀有兴趣的话
this should be useful.
这儿有好东西哦
Is this a drawing of where the ritual takes place?
这是祭祀场的图画吗？
Yes. It's on the western edge of the outer court.
对 外廷的最西边
It's called the Altar of the Sapphire Sky.
不是有座苍穹坛吗？
It's a very strange design, right?
里面的构造很特殊吧？
There's a large beam hanging from the roof.
天花板上吊着一根大柱子
There's a large drape over the central ritual altar.
中央祭坛上则垂挂着布帛
They lower the beam each time to add ceremonial texts.
每次祭祀时都会把柱子放下来 在布帛补上祝文
You're very knowledgeable.
您真了解呢
Yes. I'm not proud of this, but before working at the archives,
说来惭愧 我来书库之前
I had a more proper position at the Ministry of Rites.
原本是在礼部担任要职的
I said something
但我对上司说了些多余的话
to upset the higher-ups, and I was sent here.
就被赶到这儿来了
At first, I was afraid of its strength or lack thereof,
一开始我还很担心强度的
but I'm glad there weren't any problems.
结果看起来没问题 我就放心了
What do you mean?
您是指什么呢？
Because they hang the pole from the ceiling, like this.
柱子不是像这样吊在天花板上吗？
It's a very large pole,
那可是很大的柱子
so I was afraid that it could potentially fall.
我很担心会掉下来
When I asked about its strength,
就对强度提出了建言
I was demoted to work here.
结果就被贬到这儿了
That could be very terrifying.
这的确是很可怕
If the metal fittings that fix the pole broke,
要是固定柱子的金属配件坏了
and the pole fell from the ceiling, then the person
柱子就会从天花板上掉下来
most at risk would be the performer of the ritual, who would be right underneath.
最危险的莫过于在下方主持祭祀的人
Someone of nobility.
某个贵人将成为牺牲品
An issue with strength and stability…
强度的问题…
But which ritual item was stolen?
但是 到底偷了什么祭器呢？
If such a valuable item was stolen, surely they'd make a new one…
如此重要的祭器不见的话 一定会重新制作
Make a new one…
重新制作…
Excuse me.
不好意思
When will they hold a ceremony in this hall next?
这座祭坛下次举行祭祀是何时？
When?
何时？
Right. That would be today.
啊 正好是今天
If my speculation is correct,
如果我猜得没错
this has been planned for a very long time.
这应该是花上很长时间 精心拟定的计划
There's no certainty that every part will work.
每个事件都不能确保成功
But by setting several traps, a few of them will overlap.
但若设计重重机关 将其中几个事件累积起来
That is how they led up to this moment.
最后在这儿连结起来
It's just speculation, nothing more.
这纯粹只是猜测 不过是猜测罢了
But what if that speculation was right?
但若是猜中的话会怎么样？
Here it is!
是那儿吧
ALTAR OF THE SAPPHIRE SKY
（苍穹坛）
Hey! What are you doing?
喂！你要做什么？
Please let me through!
请让我过去！
-I can't allow that. -It's an emergency!
-不行 -这是紧急情况
A maidservant like you cannot intervene in festivities!
就你这样的婢女也想干涉祭祀吗？
He's right. I'm just a maid.
他说得没错 我只是个婢女
I have no power.
没有任何权力
But once something happens, it's too late.
但等到发生事情就太迟了
That's how irreparable things always happen!
无法挽回的事情总是这样发生的
Someone's life is at risk.
这件事攸关性命
Please cancel the festivities!
请停止祭祀
That's not something for you to decide.
这不是你说了算
If you want to say something,
有意见的话
write a comment in the suggestion box.
先投书到招谏箱再说吧
-It'll be too late then! -I won't allow it!
-那样就来不及了 -不准！
There is a major fault with the ritual altar.
那个祭坛有致命的缺陷
Someone could have tampered with it.
可能有人动过手脚
If you don't let me in right now,
如果现在不让我进去
you'll regret it!
您会后悔的！
I'm telling you that there's danger.
我已经像这样劝告过有危险了
And yet, you refuse to hear of it.
您却还是拒绝的话…
Right. I see what's going on.
哎呀 莫非是这么回事吗？
It makes sense. You intend to get in my way to make sure
原来如此 您是要妨碍我
that the scheme plays out.
然后等着出事 对吧？
Perhaps you're connected to whoever plotted all this.
也就是说 您跟动手脚的人是一伙的
I'm about to lose consciousness…
快晕过去了
It must be infuriating to be talked to that way by a little girl.
被一个丫头这样说 当然会生气了
I taunted him on purpose. This was bound to happen.
我是故意刺激他的 没办法
But this incident isn't enough.
但这点骚动行不通的
A small fight like this
祭祀不会因为这种小骚动
couldn't stop the festivities.
停下来的
I'm all right.
没什么大不了的
I can't afford to lose consciousness now.
我还不能失去意识
Are you done?
大人满意了吗？
Please let me through.
请让我过去
There's someone of noble blood inside, correct?
里面有位身分尊贵的大人吧？
If something happens, wouldn't it be all of you who are beheaded?
要是发生什么事 到时掉脑袋的会是您吧？
I'm not asking you to stop the festivities.
我不是要您中断祭祀
Just let me go.
只要您放我过去
Just say a rat sneaked in by accident.
您就说不小心让老鼠溜进去了
In that case, I'd be the only one being beheaded!
这样的话 只有我丢掉脑袋就够了！
You're saying I should believe a little girl like you?
你要我相信你一个丫头说的话吗？
How about my word then?
那么 我说的话如何呢？
You are…
你是…
And anyways,
话说回来
what are you doing, beating up a little girl like that?
殴打年轻姑娘成何体统？
She's hurt.
都把人打伤了 不是吗？
Anyways,
总而言之
what if you listen to the girl this one time?
就照着姑娘说的做如何？
I'll take full responsibility for this.
责任由我来承担
I don't want to see who's behind me.
我不想看是谁在背后
And he came at such perfect timing, like he calculated it…
出现的时机就像是算好了一样
Now's not the time to think about these things.
不 现在不是在意这种事情的时候
I don't care who's behind me.
是谁在说话都无所谓
I probably look terrible.
我看起来一定很惨
I'll ask Sir Gaoshun,
在一切结束后
and once everything is over, I'll take a nice, long bath.
拜托高顺大人让我慢慢洗个澡吧
I have to make sure
在那之前
not to get beheaded before that.
得先确保脑袋不会搬家才行
I made it…
赶上了…
I should stitch that up.
得缝起来才行
Hey.
喂
How did this happen?
怎么会变成这种状况？
Sir Jinshi.
壬氏大人
Could I have the calculus bovis?
能赐牛黄给小的吗？
Now's not the time for that.
不是说这个的时候吧？
What happened
发生什么事了？
to your face?
你的脸怎么…
Why is Sir Jinshi here?
为什么壬氏大人在这儿？
Why does he look so sad?
为什么他会露出这种表情？
I'm sorry. Let me stitch up my leg…
不好意思 先让小的把腿…
Hey!
喂！
Hey! Hang in there!
喂 振作点
Wake up!
醒醒
Hey!
喂！
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next episode, "Thornapple."
下一集 《曼陀罗花》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：杨易